Welcome to the first episode of the BugBash Podcast, where we talk about all things software correctness and reliability.
I'm your host, David Nguyen.
To kick things off, we thought we'd start with the beginning of FoundationDB.
Today, all three founders will be talking through the story of FoundationDB, from an idea all the way through acquisition by Apple.
Whether you're interested in the underlying technology or the journey to market, you'll want to stick around.
Okay, hey, I'm Dave Rosenthal, and I was one of the co-founders of FoundationDB, along with these gentlemen.
And I was sort of, Dave and I were the ones really responsible for the technology, the architecture, the kind of initial, you know, coding up of FoundationDB.
I'm Dave Scherer.
I, you know, after Dave took over as CEO of the company, I was the CTO.
Before that, we were just sort of undifferentiated co-founders.
And you know, I'm, you know, I would say that the technology was the part that I focused on.
Nick Lavezzo, I ran the parts of the company that were not coding or sales basically.
So made the trains run on time.
Chief Operating Officer once we took titles.
We were sitting down to talk about starting a number of different things.
Like we had lots of business ideas.
And a Twitter, like a Twitter that wouldn't fail all the time.
Yeah, we had lots of things we were talking about from, you know, from air conditioning to, you know, and basically all of them had in common that we were going to have to run some kind of scalable service.
And so, you know, being the nerds that we are, we started talking about what technology stack we would use to implement things, like even before we, you know, fully decided on which idea we were going to pursue.
And we basically found decent answers for like all the pieces of that puzzle until we came to look at what kind of database we would use.
And then we did not like the answers.
And, you know, at the time, you know, this would have been 2009-ish, I think.
You know, basically your choices were sort of like relational databases that were sort of like, you know, relics of the 90s in a sort of like pre-scale world.
Or like, you know, or databases that gave up completely on any form of concurrency control in order to scale well.
Yeah.
And it was the beginning era of sort of NoSQL databases, these sort of cloud databases, but all of them had sort of thrown the baby out with the bathwater to try to make, is like, and as long as it can scale, it's no matter what other compromises we made, it was okay.
So there was these like two obvious options, both of which sort of had these huge obvious flaws.
That's right.
And people at the time had convinced themselves that like the CAP theorem meant that you fundamentally couldn't have high availability and like transactions.
And, you know, we were able to convince ourselves that that was not actually a fundamental limitation.
Yeah, slowly.
Yeah, that's right.
Because when it says theorem, you're like, huh?
Right.
No, that's right.
And so the, you know, and basically after thinking about that a while and coming up with a solution that seemed like it would work well, we basically decided that that was more important than any of the things we had wanted it for and decided to just pursue that.
You know, so obviously the next question after deciding that you can have some concurrency control is like, what kind of data model you're going to have.
And it seemed wrong to us that either everybody be forced to adopt exactly one data model for everything or that people have to go through the extremely difficult process of building a distributed transactional database, you know, for each possible data model.
And so we came up with a layered architecture where we would build a transactional distributed storage engine.
Bottom layer.
That's right.
That's the foundation in FoundationDB.
And then build like any number of different, you know, like systems that would normally be stateful, you know, from relational databases to, you know, queues to search engines to whatever on top of it, like, you know, with minimal abstraction penalty.
And so, you know, that was the design we were pursuing from the beginning.
Yeah, so I guess the company was called FoundationDB, but really, it should have been called like Foundation SE or something, because we actually only built like half of a database, really.
We built, the focus of the company was really on this storage engine layer.
And, you know, we sort of had, we had grand plans to eventually build all the possible databases possible on top of it.
But the sort of core technology of FoundationDB really, in the simulation framework and all of that stuff, was really most relevant for this storage engine that we built.
Yeah.
And we haven't talked yet about ACID transactions and what that actually means.
But basically, it's really high levels of data consistency guarantees that you get in like a relational, single machine relational databases like, you know, MySQL or whatever.
And we were, the very novel thing about what we were doing was providing ACID transactions in a distributed database, where there's one database across many machines.
And those, having that data consistency guarantees of ACID transactions allowed that storage layer to be super reliable so that you could build a lot of different data models on top of it and get those guarantees.
To expand on that, in addition to the direct benefits of having concurrency control, like at the application layer or whatever, because you can use transactions to maintain a high level invariant using low level operations.
Without that level of concurrency control, if you have a key value store, but you want a relational table, there's no way to get from one to the other.
Like, because a single operation on the high level data model may require multiple operations on different things.
Say a primary index and a secondary index in the low level data model, and if you have no way to do those atomically or with isolation, then you basically have to start over and build a new database for the high level thing.
So that extra feature of concurrency control was also a vital enabling technology for the layered architecture.
Because technology forced us to build the storage engine first, like the first product that we had on the market was basically a distributed storage engine, a transactional key value store.
And that appeals to people who are either going to basically build a high level database themselves, Snowflake was one of our early customers, or people who are doing something unusual enough that they really need to be able to customize their data model at a low level, or people who just like to reinvent the wheel.
And I say this with love because I like to reinvent the wheel myself.
Yeah, in a way, it was a funny, it's like a small sliver because it was like people who, like regular databases aren't good enough, they want to build their own, but they don't quite want to build the storage engine.
And it was like that was our first, first group of people that wanted to use FoundationDB.
And the biggest challenge with that from a business perspective is just that it makes for, in essence, a extremely long sales cycle.
Like you have somebody who's building a Greenfield project because otherwise switching databases is really hard and switching databases to a lower level database than you started with is extremely hard.
And then they have to decide to adopt it, build their product, and then launch it and then scale up to the point where they're spending significant money with us.
And for example, I don't know exactly how much Snowflake paid us before we got acquired, but it was not a lot of money.
It would have been a huge amount of money a few years later, but that long sales cycle was very challenging.
And towards the end of the company, we were starting to develop those higher level databases that could be more naturally and broadly adopted, but we didn't get very far into the market with them.
I think to answer the question also, how the market reacted initially.
So we were outed by one of our investors.
He posted our website to Hacker News before we had anything available for download or really had written anything intelligent about what we were doing.
And I think we were basically laughed at.
People were like, this is not possible.
You can't make a database with ACID transactions that's horizontally scalable.
And I think we got into some battles in the comments section.
The kind of conventional wisdom was you couldn't do this.
Yeah, and then we basically rushed to...
Well, then we went to TechCrunch Disrupt with a very early demo that we built that was actually this amazing physical thing where we had a little...
I mean, we printed out on a piece of printer paper, break our database, and there was a little cluster of five machines.
And Dave put this together with these little spinny, like a graphic.
Yeah, well, we realized that we had the most boring product in the world to demo, because it was like, you see, it's still running.
And it's still, and it's just like a blinking cursor.
No, trust me, it's up.
So yeah, we made these little five mini computers and each one had a little screen.
And we're like, okay, this is still boring.
It's still five cursors.
So we made this little spinning thing that was irrelevant, but it showed numbers incrementing.
And so you would sort of see these five computers on the booth.
And like, they're all spinning together and you're like, what the heck's going on?
And so people would come in and they try to unplug the databases.
And then some wise guy, of course, would try to pull out the network switch or shut the whole system down.
And we kind of had like, we had talking lines for all of this stuff were like, so it's durable.
And so yeah, but that was sort of one of the first demos we did to the world.
People still tell me about that.
That got us on the front page of TechCrunch during Disrupt.
We weren't actually participating in Disrupt, except we had a little table, and we got all this attention on the end of the first day, which led to a bunch of conversations.
And then after that, it was kind of a sprint to get something downloadable on the website.
And once that was done, I think people slowly started to be like, wait a minute, maybe these guys aren't actually lying.
Yeah, that was a fantastic demo.
I think that in a lot of ways, the fact that conventional wisdom was that what we were doing was impossible really aided us in our marketing.
Because first of all, that just makes it a really interesting topic of conversation, right?
Like, you know, but secondly, because I think it's the nature of engineers to be skeptical.
And you basically have two different paths of skepticism for any new technology.
One is like, that won't work.
And the other is like, yeah, that isn't really very good, or I don't really need it, or it's not important.
And like, it just happens that the former is a lot easier to objectively rebut than the latter, and that it's hard to switch tasks, switch tax once you've committed to one of those.
So, you know, we had the advantage that people would come in very skeptical that what we were doing was possible.
And, you know, then once they were convinced that it was possible, they kind of had to accept that actually it was pretty good.
Yeah, and, you know, as this relates to...
It's true.
I remember a bunch...
I remember all these calls, though, because we would...
Another...
You said, how would the market respond to us?
Well, there were a certain...
So NoSQL was kind of cool and popular at the time.
So there was a certain number of companies out there that had achieved scale, you know, I don't know, drop boxes or whoever of the world, you know.
And they were very interested in these kind of like, is there a more sophisticated database, data structure or whatever we can build?
And I remember like three or four instances where, you know, one of us, but I remember the ones that I did, had to go talk to some VP of engineering who was like, so what you're doing is impossible.
And it was literally like on a whiteboard for half an hour to try to, you know, test whether we could defend the feasibility of what we claimed we were doing, which was kind of funny because they could also try it and run it, you know.
But they just every, you know, people kind of, it was like we had to pass the whiteboard test too, because people thought it was smoke and mirrors a little bit, yeah.
And this relates, I think, to antithesis pretty well too, because, you know, what we're doing in antithesis is also another thing that sounds impossible, right?
It was like we're building this fully deterministic environment that can run all your software with perfect reproducibility and intelligent exploration of all of these paths and everything.
And so we were expecting to go out into the world and, you know, get this sort of same reaction of like, you know, and have to prove ourselves.
But the benefit of the FoundationDB story is that when we launched and had our sort of coming out, we really didn't encounter the same level and nowhere near the same level of skepticism.
And in fact, had a lot of people be like, wait, this sounds impossible.
But that's the FoundationDB people.
Like, it's probably real.
I think also there just doesn't happen to have been like 50,000 like think pieces written about how this specific thing is impossible, that like a lot of people have like learned to use it as a like, you know, as a like way to sound smart or whatever.
But so we knew from the very beginning that like testing was going to be a extremely difficult and extremely vital thing.
Like, you know, we did not have to find out the hard way that we didn't want to get a call from a customer at 3 a.m. being like, we think your database is corrupted.
We don't know how.
We don't know why.
We can't reproduce it, but everything is down.
You know, you have to fix it right now.
You know, that was completely foreseeable if we built a distributed transactional data store that didn't work.
Again, that layered architecture means that like a little bit of wrong answers at the lowest level can cause who knows what kind of invariant violations at higher level.
So we basically had to build something that was perfect or the next thing to perfect.
And, you know, and we're trying to build this very, very strong concurrency control model on top of the like very, very weak model of machines that can fail, reboot, go slow, go fast, like get disconnected from each other, get partitioned, you know, have network packets delivered out of order, you know, just like a, you know, like a very, very challenging low level model.
And hard to debug set of problems.
Yes.
And additionally, all of those problems are things that are like somewhat hard to simulate, you know, hard.
They're not in your code.
And very hard to reproduce.
That if something goes wrong, and so, you know, we thought about, you know, building, you know, non-deterministic, you know, fault tolerance tests for it, which is one of the obvious things to do, and realized that every time it found a problem, it was basically going to be giving us like one bit, like there's a problem.
And maybe if we're lucky, some blogs that would not have enough information, because it's like not feasible to log all the information you would need.
And so we decided to go a relatively radical path from the very beginning.
Dave and I had built a simulation at a previous company, Visual Sciences, that was actually more around performance of a distributed system than correctness.
And that had been more, you would almost call it more like model checking in the modern terminology, in that it wasn't like, the simulation wasn't running the real code of the thing.
But we had had some pretty good experience with that as a way of understanding the many different ways something can play out.
And we, you know, someone inspired by that came up with this approach to deterministic simulation testing, where we would take the real software of the program and run it in a simulation, you know, all single threaded and deterministic with every interaction with the outside worlds, you know, running through a simulator that could control everything.
And that took a lot of building.
It was not a trivial thing to do.
And it made architectural constraints on the database we could build.
We built, you know, a multi-process, single threaded model so that we wouldn't have threading as a source of non-determinism.
Yeah, thread it per core, yeah.
We built a dialect of C++ to do asynchronous programming in it.
So we had a big investment in that with the goal of having tests that we could really trust that would tell us that the software had all of these very ambitious properties that we were trying to make it have.
You know, that wasn't a completely smooth path.
I find very memorable.
It was probably sort of like a few months after we sort of finished the first version of the simulator and started actually building our database.
It probably didn't even like write anything to disk yet.
Yeah, no, that's true.
We're talking in an early...
It's like you have to imagine this thing that was a sim...
It sort of started as a full simu...
It started as like a whiteboard and thoughts, and then it became sort of a mock-up and a simulation, and then it was probably a period of like two years that the sort of simulated database sort of gradually turned into a real database but programmed with the same framework, which was the goal.
That's right.
Yeah, no, that's right.
We definitely built...
An early bug.
That's right.
We built the simulation of a database first, but while we were still building the simulation of the database, we discovered a bug, I think just by code review in our commit pathway that was very, very severe, and yet our tests were all green.
And that was very disturbing because we were counting on those tests to help us do this very difficult thing.
And again, because we knew that once our thing was in production, we would need to count on them to deliver like essentially zero production bugs.
And so, you know, that was really a moment when the whole enterprise seemed in doubt.
You know, we didn't know, like it seemed like this approach at testing had failed us in a way, and that without it, we weren't sure what else we could do to accomplish the goal at all.
And so, you know, we spent a fair amount of time talking about it and analyzing what went wrong.
You know, and again, we basically ultimately decided that we were on the right path, but that we just needed a lot more investment.
Double down on testing.
Yeah.
In the simulation.
I don't remember the bug, but I remember the like conversations about just like, how much do we want to check ourselves and redouble our efforts on simulation and testing?
And that after a week of debating it or something like that, we were like, we need to do this.
And I don't know what you remember, but you mentioned two reasons for the simulation framework.
One of which is being able to easily debug it, the deterministic reproduction of the bug.
And I kind of feel like that was like a nice side effect.
And the real fundamental goal was just like the guarantee that nothing was wrong.
The green light at the end of the test was the thing that we really want.
And if for some weird reason, it had been hard to debug things in this environment, we still almost would have wanted only the green light.
But the happy thing about the deterministic simulation solution was that you kind of get both properties.
That's absolutely true.
I think because our need for correctness was so great, we absolutely would have done things that were hard to debug.
And indeed we did.
Like we built, for example, because we trusted nothing.
I was going to say the call stack makes it hard to debug and flow.
That's right.
But I was going to say we built, we did build a physical fault tolerance testing setup with electronically controlled power switches.
With sand.
That's right.
Like in order to be a validator essentially for the simulation.
Because what if we're wrong and there were bugs that it couldn't find?
That system for all of the expense, because it did actually burn through a lot of computers, it turns out that the thing where you shouldn't unplug computers while they're running is not an urban legend.
But it only ever found two problems.
The first was that our one dependency, Apache Zookeeper, had some bugs that were serious enough to cause...
We did.
We replaced it with our...
Immediately after finding the bug with quicksand the first night.
Wow.
Yes.
Did we write our own?
We wrote our own Paxos implementation to replace it.
Basically, because we couldn't simulate Zookeeper in our simulation due to its limitations, and so we had to just count on it to do what we thought it would do.
When we found that that assumption was violated, we basically decided to rebuild it.
And by that time, with the simulation framework where it is, like deciding to write a new Paxos implementation in a week or two and test it and trust it was actually not insane.
It was not a big deal.
No, that was the easiest decision ever.
But just to get a picture for this physical validation cluster, we had these mini-motherboards, and we went into my basement and got a circular saw and cut a piece of plywood in a few pieces.
And the whole thing was just a few of these boards just screwed in with like two screws, I think, you know, each and just into the big piece of plywood.
And then a few like network switches zip tied on and set up in a way that could create network partitions given power failures.
And then yeah, this relay controlled thing we found on Amazon that turned power on and off that, you know, failed every couple months and because relays aren't designed for, you know, for line voltage.
But but yeah, this thing just sat in our office just click clacking, click clacking and we'd come in and yeah, like the first morning or two, you know, it found some problems and pretty shortly thereafter none.
Yeah, the other bug that it found was actually kind of funny.
It turns out that the installation of FoundationDB was not durable.
So we would install a version of the database on the cluster and then start it running.
And then the power of some machine would fail and it would reboot and it would come back up.
And the database file was there intact and with everything durable.
But the database wasn't installed on the machine anymore, so it wouldn't rejoin the cluster.
Test harness failure.
We actually fixed it.
We put a sink in our install to ensure that once you installed FoundationDB on the system, installation completed, power failure wouldn't uninstall it.
I think that if there were other people doing the exact same thing, we were not informed by it.
That's for sure true.
I was saying, you know, there was something I was thinking back to, though, Dave, which was, so Dave and I worked on a video game together when we were kids.
We were like 14 or something and started working on it.
But the execution, so it ended up being a multiplayer video game.
And this video game actually had every player in the game was running their own version of the whole world, and it had to simulate the whole world.
And so this, I mean, that's not how a video game today would work, to be very clear.
Like it would definitely work with a client and a server.
But we, I mean, I don't know, we didn't like want to run server.
I didn't even know how to do that.
So we were like, OK, the clients will figure out how to work together.
And so to make that model work, you have to have the same simulation run on every client.
And so we learned actually in that experience about this idea of determinism and what the heck that is, and why it's really annoying to try to fix things without it, because we would literally get in these games, and Dave would be like, I destroyed you, and I'll be like, I'm winning, what do you mean?
And we'd be like, oh no, it's desynced again, you know.
I would probably actually be losing in both multiverses, but that's fine.
But at any rate, we eventually sort of figured out how to add in some debugging to make sure there was determinism and kind of beat down all the sources of determinism.
So I mean, I'm sure you remember this.
This was not a hypervisor, but it was like the early experience in sort of the value of this property in debugging and engineering.
And it also, I think, is one of the things that gave us confidence that we could implement the database code in a naturally deterministic way.
Like again, without a hypervisor or whatever, like part of the burden of this approach is that you need to make sure that all of the code in the system under test is written deterministically.
You can detect failures of that and go fix them, but you have to fix them manually.
But you're right, of all the scary missions we faced, we were like, oh, determinism, oh, we can do that.
That's right.
It's like a little bit of a pain in the neck.
You have to watch out for some data structures that-
Memory addresses.
Sort things by pointers and that sort of thing, but it's generally achievable.
Again, if you're writing a single threaded asynchronous program with no dependencies, which is not everybody.
Which is what we decided to do.
I think it's fantastic that it's open source.
I think basically Ben Collins gets full credit for that, because it made 100 percent sense for Apple to do it, but it making sense is not enough reason for a big company to do something.
It takes a lot of work to make it actually happen, and that was basically all in Ben.
I think it's very valuable, so it's great that it's out there for people to use.
I think, you know, without, you know, the company that we might have built maybe would have done a better job of building a huge ecosystem above it if it had succeeded, but then again, it might not have.
So you know, I think all in all, it's a pretty decent outcome.
It's really cool to see for me, people starting to, I mean, still using FoundationDB quite a few years later.
I think one of the sad things is that it sort of said another way.
Most of the companies that have built layers on top of FoundationDB have found the resultant system so valuable that they've kept it for themselves.
So there's actually not a, you know, Snowflake.
I mean, well, Snowflake did a lot of work, but metadata system was built on FoundationDB.
But we know gaming companies and AI companies and many companies that have built their own sort of custom internal file systems or data structures, that FoundationDB is the kind of storage engine core.
But again, they found the resultant systems are valuable.
They haven't really open sourced it.
So I'm really looking forward to the day maybe when we get some of these companies that have done serious engineering work on top of FoundationDB because we know these layers exist, but none of them have really been released, the very powerful layers to the world.
I think Apple has put out a reasonably powerful one in record layer and stuff, but there's a lot more out there that people don't talk about.
I think that people are most, I think they come attracted to the reliability because a lot of companies that think about building their, say their own custom data store of some nature or another.
Basically, it's well-established lore in the distributed systems world that this is really hard, and it's going to be years and years of engineering to get it right.
So FoundationDB has a sterling reputation for solving that corner of the problem, and then it also has a reputation for being pretty bare bones in terms of what it provides.
So to some people, that's a turn-off.
It's like, oh, this isn't actually a database.
But for a certain set of people, that's like a turn on.
And it's like, oh, wow, it solves the hard problems, and it gives me just this bare key value raw flexibility.
So those are the kind of people that have built stuff on it.
We did everything that we could to make it so that systems built on top of it could inherit its reliability and operational properties.
Like again, you know, defaulting to extremely strong consistency.
And I'm gonna put this exactly, like we optimized the performance for the like strongest concurrency control modes, so that there's less temptation to give them up for performance.
Like it's possible for a system to be configurable, to be serializable, but it does that through some like incredibly expensive kind of locking.
And if you really want good performance, you've got to like dip down to lower modes.
So by doing that, we make it so that if you build something on top that doesn't like turn off all the safety features, like, you know, you're, you know, basically because, like, essentially the property is that if, if each transaction that you do would preserve some invariant of the data store, and the transactions are serializable, then any collection of transactions will also preserve that invariant.
And so that makes it relatively easy to build a reliable system on top.
As soon as you start being like, oh, well, I don't quite need transactionality here or, oh, I can, you know, I really need a little extra performance here and I'm going to, like, then you start taking responsibility for the hard problems.
And, you know, and you might, and it would behoove you to start doing some real, some real testing of the resulting thing.
And indeed, some FoundationDB layers have been built using FoundationDB's tools so that the people making them can test them in using FoundationDB simulation.
Like today, antithesis is another option, like, you know, because you could put FoundationDB and your layer together into a, like, single system and just test it with antithesis, even if the layer is built in some completely different way.
I guess, I think if somebody asked me that, like, you know, hey, if I build a layer on top of FoundationDB, is it going to be as solid as FoundationDB?
Like, or, I mean, I think the easy answer is like, actually, yes, that's quite simple, because if, as long as you adhere to the basic design principle that you leave everything stateless, everything stateful is in FoundationDB and the layer on top is just sort of stateless.
And if you talk to anybody who, like, operates a system at scale or tries to scale a system, I mean, all of the concerns about reliability and scalability are pretty much 99 percent.
They're in the stateful parts of the system.
That's the messy part.
So with FoundationDB, we sort of handled the stateful part, and the layer stuff most of the time is built as a purely stateless, sort of almost just sort of converting a high level user command into low level key value manipulations.
And as long as you adhere to that basic sort of intended architecture of FoundationDB, you really do sort of get the rest of the properties for free, and you just need to deal a little bit with kind of making sure you have a good pool of running layer nodes, you know, and a load balancer and stuff like that.
We could not have built it with the team and budget that we had without the deterministic simulation testing.
Like, I think it's remotely possible that a much bigger and more expensive project could have done it using equally aggressive non-deterministic fault tolerance tests, you know, and paying the various prices of that.
But I don't think we would have, no.
Yeah, I guess somebody could have tried to just stuff a lot of log statements in and run a lot of tests and debug it.
But look, the thing is, maybe we could have gotten it across the finish line in theory, the V1 of it.
But the amazing thing about the deterministic simulation testing to me, was that as the team scaled up and we brought in like interns and other engineers, and we could continue to make rapid progress on the system because of the confidence that we had in the testing.
And I mean, we used to say, like, as long as it passed our test, we had the speed test and the correctness test.
As long as it, I mean, it could have been a bunch of random commits from anybody.
As long as it's passing the test, we would like to ship it to customers, you know?
So that kind of confidence is rare in software development, even rarer in building something as sensitive as a database.
And that I think was the most sort of, you know, surprising thing for me about the kind of knock on benefits, you know, past sort of, past the initial system implementation, we sort of kept velocity for a long time.
I think, like, a concrete example of that is, we rewrote the transaction processing guts of the system for a, what, like, 14x speed increase or something.
Greater scalability, basically, I think, was...
Sure, but for, you know, two or three people working on it for a couple months.
And that's just unthinkable for any other normal database company that didn't have this kind of magic testing where you could throw, you know, the new commits or whatever over the fence and find out, oh, I screwed this up, I will fix that, you know.
Another...
Something that I think some people find relatively shocking is that we did not have a pre-commit code review flow at FoundationDB.
Like, if an engineer had confidence in the thing they were working on and the tests were passing, they would just merge it.
We did try to code review all our code eventually because there's dimensions of code quality and things other than the testing can't catch.
But generally, we knew that something that even passed a relatively modest amount of our testing was not going to break everybody else who was working on it, or make it hard for people to continue working, and that before the thing got into release, it would get a massive amount of CPU hours of testing that would really ensure it was right.
And so, that really helped speed us up.
It really helped give us confidence to do things that other companies would have hesitated to do.
We already talked about rewriting the Paxos implementation, which is the kind of thing that anyone with any sense thinks is very terrifying.
So, after that early moment of doubt, our doubling down really did get us to the point, not cheaply, I would guess the company put something close to a third of its total engineering effort into testing over time, but it got us to the point where we really did have that confidence and it made us able to do things we couldn't otherwise have done.
Yeah, we had no code review before commit.
It was, as I said, if the test passed, we felt good about the artifact at the end of the day.
There was this other aspect of how do you build a maintainable code base, but that's a totally different problem.
Our testing evolved over time though, right?
I mean, so we sort of first ran basic deterministic tests, and we would try to do things like delay packets, but we sort of had a...
There was like an informal competition, you know, internally, to try to come up with the sort of test situations or techniques that would cause the most problems.
I feel like I remember something called swizzle...
Swizzle clogging.
Yes, so ultimately, we came up with this thing, swizzle clogging, which is basically probably like a horribly primitive version of the kind of thing that antithesis does now.
But basically, it would clog up the network connections between machines, shut them off sort of in a random order, like maybe lose power somewhere, and then turn them on in another random order.
And this sort of like maximally induced, you know, sort of the kind of weird cases where one packet arrives before the other in some weird sequence.
And so, yes, swizzle clogging was...
But I mean, at some point, we really felt strongly that just a night of testing was, you know, like billions of hours of real world, you know, failure situation.
Because we were able to do it in, you know, this massively parallel way, but the conditions we were emulating were just so much worse than the real world.
That's great.
And, you know, we also developed over time, like, techniques for measuring how good a job we were doing of getting the system into different states and testing things.
You know, we invented the, you know, something equivalent to, you know, antithesis is sometimes assertions that can say, look, this code should be tested in this particular way.
And if this isn't hit in test, it means some kind of failure of our testing that we need to address.
And, you know, that helped us to, over time, you know, like produce that level of confidence.
Thanks for checking out The BugBash Podcast.
If you want to reach out, maybe with an idea for the show, or maybe you want to be on it, send us an email at bugbash at antithesis.com.
Or if chats more your style, head over to antithesis.com and scroll to the bottom, where you'll find the link to our Discord.
Until next time.